Guide to the C. Doris Hellman Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
C. Doris Hellman Papers,
[ca. 1925]-1973
Hellman, Clarisse Doris, 1910-
ca. 27,000 items (61 boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4078882
Biographical Note
Historian. Hellman (1910-1973) was Professor of Social Studies at Pratt Institute, 1951-1956; and Professor of history, Queens College, 1957-1973. (Vassar College A.B., 1930; Radcliffe College A.M., 1931; Columbia University Ph.D., 1933). She was married to Morton Pepper.
Scope and Content
The correspondence, manuscripts, notes, speeches, documents, and related printed materials of Hellman, reflecting her specialty as an historian of 16th and 17th century astronomers and astronomy as well as ancient, medieval, and Renaissance science. Included in her professional correspondence are numerous letters from George Sarton and Lynn Thorndike. College records, class materials and class notes document the development of her academic career beginning with her undergraduate career at Vassar. Numerous lecture notes, class notes and working papers reflect her teaching, research and lectures at New York University, Cornell, the Columbia University Renaissance Seminar, and her active participation in professional organizations such as the History of Science Society. Of particular interest are eight boxes of notes and related printed materials concerning astronomy, astronomers, and the history of science.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 16 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Uncataloged Correspondence
Series III: Manuscripts
Series IV: Speeches
Series V: Publication File
Series VI: Name File
Series VII: George Sarton
Series VIII: History of Science
Series IX: Meetings, etc
Series X: National Science Foundation
Series XI Education
Series XII: Biographical
Series XIII: Photographs
Series XIV: Jewish Foundation for the Education of Girls
Series XV: Printed Materials
Series XVI: May 1974 Gift
Subjects
Queens College (New York, N.Y.)--Faculty.; Radcliffe College--Students.; Vassar College--Students.; New York University.; Cornell University.; Columbia University--Students.; Pratt Institute--Faculty.; History of Science Society.; Sarton, George, 1884-1956.; Thorndike, Lynn, 1882-1965.; Pepper, Morton.; Astronomy--History.; Science--History.; History--Study and teaching.; History--Research.; Women college teachers.; Historians.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
1974 M-74 Pepper, Morton Gift
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Sarton, George To Doris C. Hellman, (1 box)
  - Throndike, Lynn To Doris C. Hellman, (1 box)
- Series II: Uncataloged Correspondence
  - Uncataloged Correspondents, (7 boxes) (Box 1-7)
- Series III: Manuscripts
  - Comet of 1577. Manuscripts, (5 boxes) (Box 8-12)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts, (4 boxes) (Box 13-16)
- Series IV: Speeches
  - Speeches (Box 17)
- Series V: Publication File
  - Publication File, (3 boxes) (Box 18-20)
- Series VI: Name File
  - A - Brahe (Box 21)
  - Brahe - C (Box 22)
  - D - Gl (Box 23)
  - Gr - K (Box 24)
  - L - M (Box 25)
  - N - Re (Box 26)
  - Ri - Sp (Box 27)
  - St - Z (Box 28)
- Series VII: George Sarton
  - George Sarton materials (Box 29)
- Series VIII: History of Science
  - History of Science Society, 1949-1967 (Box 30)
- Series IX: Meetings, etc.
  - Organizational meetings & conferences, (6 boxes) (Box 31-36)
- Series X: National Science Foundation
  - National Science Foundation materials (Box 37 & 38)
- Series XI Education
  - Class materials (Box 39-43)
  - CUNY materials (Box 44)
  - CUNY, NYU & Cornell materials (Box 45)
  - Columbia University materials: Class Notes (Box 46)
  - Columbia University materials: Notes & Papers (Box 47)
  - Vassar materials (Box 48)
- Series XII: Biographical
  - Biographical materails (Box 48)
- Series XIII: Photographs
  - Photographs (Box 48)
- Series XIV: Jewish Foundation for the Education of Girls
  - Jewish Foundation for the Education of Girls (Box 49)
- Series XV: Printed Materials
  - Printed materials, inscribed, (5 boxes) (Box 50-54)
  - Printed materials, (3 boxes) (Box 55-57)
- Series XVI: May 1974 Gift
  - Fifth copy of manuscript of The Comet
    [Interfiled with above]
  - Sixth copy of manuscript of The Comet
    [Interfiled with above. Gift of Morton Pepper, July 1974]
  - Math, physics, French and german notes of C.D. Hellman, ca.1924-1930 (Box 58 & 59)
  - College Social Studies notes of CDH (Box 60)
    [Gift of Morton Pepper, July 1974]
  - Clippings and printed memorabilia (Box 61)
  - Paul Ruben Cooper's dissertation on Eva Le Gallienne, 1967 (Box 61)
  - Several items of family correspondence (Box 61)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts and documents (Box 61)
  - Photographs (Box 61)